Now, in the previous few lectures, we discussed about the planning capability of AI agent
that we looked at tools and action.
Now, let us go ahead and discuss in more detail the memory capability of AI agents.
And there could be two types of memory that it can possess, one is the shorter memory
and other is the long term memory.
So, now, remember that AI agents are driven by large language models and large language
models are stateless.
They have no memory, so let us say if I send a request to an agent driven by a large
language model and let us say it gives me a response.
Now, let us say as a follow up question which has a context to the first query that I had
sent.
But for a large language model, it has no memory, it is stateless, so it would not remember
what was the previous context.
Now, to overcome this challenge, AI agents have short term memory.
Now, in the short term memory, agents retain the conversation and the user input during
the particular session.
So, whatever interaction happens with the user and AI agent, that is retain for the particular
session duration.
First we have the long term memory, the long term memory allows AI agents to retain conversation
across all previous interactions.
Now, let us say I am a user and I had an interaction with the travel agent in the month
of January 2024.
Then next, I have another conversation in the month of March 2024.
So, what it will do is, so for all the previous interaction, it will summarize the conversation
and then store it.
So, next time, let us say in September 2024, when I have a conversation with the agent,
it is going to load all the previous interactions that have been summarized.
So, now, in most cases, you can store all the previous interactions between 1 to 365 days.
And remember, most of the time, it is not the entire conversation that is stored, but it
is a summary of that interaction.
Now, let us try and understand the short term memory through an example.
Now, let us say, we have a user Joe, who is planning a two week scheme vacation.
So, once the user starts interacting with the AI agent, the first thing it does is, in the
short term memory, it will create a session ID for that particular interaction.
So, I just given a random session ID here, 2, 2, 6, 5.
So, once the AI agent gets this request and it creates a session ID, it will reply to
Joe, let me check and get back and then it goes ahead and breaks down the task and maybe
it executes certain tools, maybe it makes a call to HR system, maybe it to the hotel booking
ID.
Now, remember, if it is going to book a hotel, it needs the dates.
So, here, it is talking about mid-December, 2 weeks.
So, all this would be stored in the session ID and then maybe passed on to these tools
so that they can execute based on certain parameters.
Now, let us say, it gets a feedback saying that no rooms are available during this duration
and agent lets Joe know.
So, maybe Joe responds with new dates and those new dates are passed on to the agent and
then it executes and then completes the booking.
But now, these new dates are also stored in the short-term memory to give these tools
some context.
So, this is how a short-term memory works.
So, now, if you have to just summarize it, short-term memory agents are used to store the user
and agent interaction and they are and most likely they are stored in a data store with
a particular session ID.
Now, let us take a quick look on how the long-term memory works.
Again, let us say we have Joe and we have an AI agent and let us say he interacted with
the agent in December 2024 and he says that in its 2 weeks vacation from mid-December
but he wants the hotel rooms to be non-smoking.
And then some interaction happens between the agent and the user and let us say this user
request has been fulfilled by the AI agent and the conversation ends.
So, once the conversation between the user and AI agent ends, then what is going to happen
is it is going to probably use another large language model or the same large language
model to summarize the interaction between the user and agent and then it is going to
store that in some form of data store, maybe some service in AWS, maybe a DynamoDB.
Now, next time when Joe comes and interacts with the agent again, maybe in June 2025 and
this time he wants to plan a 2-week vacation to Egypt.
So, what will happen is before the AI agent starts responding, it will load this interaction
that was stored in the data store before it responds to the new query of Joe in June 2025.
And how does that help, now based on the previous interaction, it already knows that Joe
is looking to book hotel rooms that are non-smoking.
So, now it has an additional content, which adds an element of personalization.
Now, if we just summarize the long-term memory in agents, so what are the benefits or long-term
memory in AI agents, if you can quickly summarize, so it provides user preference to the
agent based on historical interactions, then it also gives broader contextual knowledge
to the agent, maybe microcool employees always use Hilton hotels, so it will already know
that information and it will check on the site of Hilton hotels while he is booking a hotel
for Joe.
Then as we already discussed, it summarizes all the interactions and stores in a data store
and this could be between 1 to 365 days and when a new interaction happens, all these
summarized interactions are loaded.
Okay, that is pretty much it from this lecture, I will see you in the next lecture.
Thank you.